[Music]
Stanford
University a very important Concept in
particle physics are the field equations
of course the equations of motion of the
fields describing the particles we've
described Bon Fields feron
Fields uh this the electromagnetic
field all of these fields satisfy
equations the form of the equations is
more or less wave equations and it
involves derivatives of the field with
respect to space with respect the
time and the field itself it involves
derivatives of the field and the field
itself um in other words the field
undifferentiated how do we code these
equations we just write down all of the
equations for all of the
fields yeah we could do that we could
write down the equation of motion for
the electromagnetic field for the um
electron field for all of the fields in
the system and that would uh just be the
equations of motion but
in um
standard classical mechanical systems
field Theory even Quantum field Theory
the equations of motion always come from
a lran a lran is a very important
Concept in classic iCal mechanics in
quantum mechanics and in Quantum field
Theory a lran is an object that you do
certain things to to generate all of the
equations of motion of the system not
just one by one the equations of motion
for each field but it contains in one
simple expression in one condensed
compact expression all of the equations
of
motion of a system of fields or a system
of degrees of freedom in in
general the lran IDE In classical
mechanics is very closely related to the
principle of least action we're not
going to go into that here I'm going to
just very quickly remind you of the
connection what a lanan is what it
depends on uh how you generate the
equations of motion and do one or two
examples that's that's all classical
physics and then explain to you what the
meaning of the lran is in quantum
mechanics the same lran except expressed
not in terms of classical Fields but in
terms of quantum fields
has a totally new meaning in terms of
quantum
mechanics uh that dictates the motion of
particles the interaction between
particles cross-sections for collisions
all sorts of things it codifies it in
very simple expression one
compact uh
idea okay
so lran of a system of fields
let's call it script L is a function
I'll write it l
of for the Simplicity let's just imagine
one field I'll tell you what you do if
you have more than one field but
supposing there one field
F the lran depends on the field and it
depends on the derivatives of the field
with respect to time and space so it
could depend on the derivative of the
field with the respect to time and the
derivatives of the field with respect to
X Y and
Z or more compactly it depends on the
field and the derivatives of the
field with respect to X mu this means
derivative with respect to X
mu okay all right now what do you do
with the lran to generate the field
equations I I'm not going to prove this
we're not going to argue for these
equations we've done that in the past
several times I'm just going to tell you
what the rules are the rules are to
generate the equations of motion you
differentiate the
lran with respect to the derivatives of
the
field for example derivative of L with
respect
to derivative of fi with respect to
T I'll show you an example this looks
abstract at the moment then you
differentiate with respect to
t you add to that the derivative with
respect to X of the derivative of the
lran with respect to the gradient of the
field along the x axis same thing for Y
and Z and then you set that equal to the
derivative of lran with respect to the
field itself l depends on the field
itself that is the equation of motion
for the field fi if your Lan depends on
several Fields then you do the same
thing over and over for each one of the
fields and that generates the system of
equations uh for all of the fields so as
I said we'll do an example as we go on
we'll do some examples but let's just do
the very simplest
example just to see how this works
a simple Scala field a very simple Scala
field simplest
field has a
lran which is equal to the square the
derivative of f with respect to
time squared there's a conventional 1/2
in front of it derivative of f with
respect to time squared minus the same
half derivative of five with respect to
x^2 same thing with Y and Z but I won't
write it
out oh that's a minus sign here minus
sign and then finally
minus some function and we'll call it V
of
fi or V of
f that's the nature of the lran of a
simple Scala field that's all there is
to it no more than that let's see if we
can work out what the field equations
are okay you first begin by
differentiating L grangian with respect
we could call this F dot here let's just
call it f dot the derivative of f with
respect to time and let's uh simplify
the not or condense the notation instead
of the D by DX let's write f
subx f
subx means the derivative of f with
respect to X likewise for Y and
Z yeah we that would be in
here that will be in here
okay right okay so let's first
differentiate the lran with respect to F
dot here's F dot right here F dot
squared2 5 do squar the Del derivative
with respect to Five Dot is just F dot
itself differentiate 12
f do^ 2qu with respect to F dot itself
differentiating the two cancels the 1/2
and you just get F dot but then you have
to differentiate again with respect to
time that makes it five double dot two
time derivatives second time derivative
right
then
plus now the space derivative terms come
in with the opposite sign from the time
derivative I'll explain why in a moment
but just accept it they come in with the
opposite sign so you get exactly the
same kind of thing but with the opposite
sign with second space derivatives
second derivative of five with respect
to
X2 same thing with Y and
Z and then on the right hand side we
have the derivative of lran with respect
to fi the only place where fi itself
occurs undifferentiated
is in V of
fi so what we get on the right hand side
is minus the derivative of V with
respect to
fi that's that's the form of the field
equation for a very very simple Scala
field
um some examples of
vfi the simplest example of vfi would be
a constant but then it would have no
derivative with respect to fi and it
wouldn't even contribute here not
interesting uh uh we could have
something linear in fi that's all right
you can have something linear in fi but
um if if the if this incidentally is
field energy vfi is field energy if V is
unbounded from below it means in other
words if V is just a linear function of
fi that means the energy the minimum of
the energy is infinitely far off
negative infinite that that's not good
the first interesting
example is to put f^ squ V of
f is equal to something proportional to
5^
2qu all right a proportionality needs a
constant let's call the constant M2 and
let's put a two in there's no content in
that m^2 over2 is just some
constant I call it m^2 /2 because it has
some physical meaning that we'll see in
a moment now what happens if I
differentiate m^2 / 2 5^ 2 with respect
to 5 that gives me m^2 5 differentiating
V ofi with respect to F would just give
me m^2 F all right so a again simple
wave equation F dble dot minus
derivative of f with respect to x
squared dot dot dot is equal to minus I
think m^2
F that is a very very basic form for a
wave equation both in classical field
Theory Quantum field
Theory uh electrodynamics all sorts of
situations this wave equation shows
up okay what does it say about the
relationship between the energy and
momentum of a Quantum of the field F
let's move on the quantum mechanics now
in Quantum field Theory the energy is
related to the
frequency differentiating twice always
gives us a factor of minus 2 sorry minus
Omega squar remember if we have a wave
if we have a wave function which is of
the form e to the I Omega T perhaps
times e to the minus I
KX I think I went this way
um if I differentiate with respect to
time that brings down a factor of I
minus I Omega if I do it twice it gives
me a minus Omega squar Time
5 Time 5 what happens if I differentiate
with respect to X
twice gives me two factors of K of K
subx all right so this will give me
plus K sub x^2 5 plus K sub y^ 2 plus K
sub z^ 2 all time
5 and on the right hand side we have
minus
m^2
F we can just cross off the F here
cancel it
out and what this wave equation tells us
is just a relationship between Omega and
k^2 it tells us that Omega 2 - k^2 is
equal to m
squ that's really the whole content of
the wave equation for a wave moving down
a particular axis it tells us that Omega
s is equal better yet Omega s is equal
to
k^2 plus
m^2 if we remember let's work in our
favorite units H baral Cal 1 sorry H bar
H bar = c = 1
then
Omega is nothing but the
energy right Omega is related to energy
by a factor of H bar this is energy
squared equals momentum
squared plus
m^2 this is the usual relation if I
wanted to make it I want to put the
speeds of light back in I would put uh
let's see I think a c^2 over here and a
c to the 4th over here yeah but in you
question but in units in which the speed
of light is equal to
one this is just e = E2 = p^2 + M2 this
is the usual relationship between energy
and momentum if we interpret M as the
mass of a single
Quantum okay
so what this equation tells us then is
really nothing but the relationship
between energy Mass
and
momentum with the stipulation that the
parameter M here is the mass of the
particle okay so that's quite a uh
elegant
Fact one other point in writing Lans
it's
important you want your equations in the
end to be relativistically invariant
invariant under Lorent
Transformations the only thing you have
to do to keep them invariant under the
lench Transformations is make sure that
the lran is
scaler if it's really a scaler and
transforms as a scalar in the Loren
transformation your equations of motion
will be invariant under lent
transformation that's why this minus
sign is here remember whenever uh
whenever you're doing a special
relativity there are minus
signs uh in the relationship between
space and time if you like okay so
that's the basic setup for Lans
and it's really quite simple there could
be several fields in the
lran and they could be interacting with
each other in some way or another uh let
me give you another example of just one
field supposing instead of V of f being
proportional to 5^ squar we also put in
something else for example um I don't
know G * 5
cubed right then there would be another
term in here where is it there would be
another term in
here which would be I guess minus 3G 5^
SAR the equation of motion would no
longer be linear linear means only
contains first powers of derivatives and
the field itself if an equation is
linear it means you can add Solutions
and get new
Solutions but now we have a nonlinear
term in the equations of motion
nonlinear means quadratic in fi
quadratic cubic any kind of higher power
of
fi and so we see a pattern the pattern
is things in the L grangian which are
quadratic in either derivatives or the
field itself lead to linear equations
and things which are higher Powers than
quadratic lead to nonlinear equations
nonlinear equations mean Solutions don't
add first let's take the case of linear
equations if we have linear equations
and let's suppose we have some wave
moving down an
axis it's a solution and now we have
another wave superimposed well they're
not superimposed yet it's another wave
packet from the same field moving to the
left instead of the right and they pass
each
other well if the equations of motion
are linear they will just go right
through each other that's the nature of
linear equations they'll just go right
through each other uh and the solution
will remain just after what what this is
is a certain solution what this is is a
certain solution and the sum of the two
solutions is just nothing but the two
wave packets coming at each other for
all time the solutions will just remain
the sums of the original two solutions
and all that will happen was they'll
they'll pass right through each other
and come out the other end without
scattering without
deforming uh and that's it during the
time that they pass through each other
there may be some interference but then
they'll pass through each other and uh
the two- wave packets will uh will
separate separate
undeformed on the other hand if there
are nonlinearities in the equations of
motion that means the wave packets
scatter they influence each other and
they might not only scatter they might
break up they might do all kinds of
things much more
complicated and uh that creates
scattering in particular scattering of
waves which uh which will go off and ran
you know directions uh
whatever okay so that's what
nonlinearities higher powers do here it
causes the wave packets to be nonlinear
and to
scatter another example just to show you
what you can do is you might have two
fields for Simplicity two scaler fields
to make two Scala fields
we would
take just these terms here and write
let's call it two Fields fi and uh give
me another
letter another Greek letter Sigma row
okay let's take F and row so another
possibility fori and I'm I'm not there's
nothing special about these I'm just
writing down random things uh
12 D mui s
that's the same thing I've written here
I just shortened it up and made it
simple that stands for 5 do^ 2 minus the
derivative of 5 with respect to X squ
and so forth just to give it a short
hand we do the same thing what do we
call it Row D mu row
squared and then we can add something
which some V some potential energy which
depends on both fi and row
okay so this could be some f in row
let's take an example there could be an
m^2 5^ 2 over
2 some other constant let's call it
capital m^ 2 Row 2 over
two
minus if that's all I had supposing that
was all I had then the field equations
would be uncoupled separate field
equations for fi and row
right doing this operation on five we
would get uh Five dble
Dot minus second derivative of 5 with
respect to X2 dot dot dot is equal to
m^2 minus m^ 2 5 and we get the same
kind of thing for row row double dot
minus DC row by DX s dot dot dot equal
minus big
m^2 row
in other words we would just get two
separate independent wave equations with
two different parameters little m^ s and
big m^ S and the two parameters we
correspond to the masses of the two
distinct fields or to the Quant the
masses of the Quant of the two distinct
Fields this would be a system of two
kinds of particles F Quant and row Quant
with two different masses M and Big M
Little M and Big M now now we could add
something more complicated we could add
for example let's add row * 5^ 2 again
picked at random nothing special about
this when I work out the equation of
motion for
fi we have on the right hand side the
derivative of V with respect to fi what
is the derivative of V with respect to
fi well it's just equal
to let put minus here
the derivative of V with respect to F is
just twice row
F right differentiating 5^ s just gives
me twice
5 uh on the other hand the equation of
motion for row we have to put on the
right hand side minus the derivative of
V with respect to row and that's just
equal to minus 5^
2 okay so here we see an example of an
interaction between two Fields a
terminal grangian which involves both
Fields if a terminal agian involves both
fields in some non-trivial
way okay the result will be that the
wave equation for fi will contain row
and the wave equation for row will
contain fi if in addition this is not
quadratic then the equations are
nonlinear they're nonlinear and coupled
that means that a wave packet of five
will scatter a wave packet of row and a
wave packet of row will scatter a wave
packet of five they'll come together and
uh do
things
and not just pass through each other
okay if this term is zero they'll just
pass through each
other so somehow these the terms in the
lran like row squar are telling us
something about interaction between the
Quant it's telling us that the Quant of
the field scatter each other that's what
a term like this is
indicating okay these terms here tell us
about energy and momentum this term
tells us about
Mass if we didn't have uh if we didn't
have this nonlinear term the content of
this equation would just be k s Omega s
= k^2 +
M2 that's all these terms and this term
tells us about the interaction between
quanta that's classical physics that's
classical field theory in a nutshell uh
let me write down another example for
you another
example is the dur equation well let's
first of all let's consider the da
equation what is the direct equation it
has has the form
uh I forget where the I's go
i s dot is equal
to Alpha derivative with respect to
x uh S I think there's an I here also
anybody remember I think so
plus m m beta s beta was a matrix Alpha
was a collection of three matrices this
really means alpha 1 d by dx1 plus Alpha
2 D by dx2 and so forth that was the
direct equation can it be written in
terms of lran yes it can be written in
terms of lran the lran is
just
uh I think it's i s Daga derivative of s
with respect to t s diag is the complex
conjugate of s uh plus I think it's plus
that's not very important s Daga Alpha
derivative of s with respect to
X and then finally plus s Daga beta s
time
M you'll sometimes see this is the L
grangian this lran if you do the same
operations on it will give you the dur
equation that's the lunian for the dur
equation we don't have to go through it
it's not important for us right now I
just want to indicate that there is a
lran which generates the da equation the
same way that the Scala field equation
was generated from the lunian of the
Scala
field it's got direct matrices in it so
it's a little more complicated it's a
multicomponent field field but
nevertheless that uh that direct field
is generated or the direct wave equation
is generated from the
slan okay this would just give you the
ordinary dra equation now supposing
there was another field in the problem
possibly a Scala field a Scala field a
bon field how might you you would then
add in also the Lan for the Scala field
in other words
where is it uh the scal of field L
grangian maybe with just the m s or
maybe the mq 5 Cube term is that
parenthesis in the right place I mean
you have the I over the holding I don't
remember maybe not is it important not
important not important to us uh the
important thing is that we can couple
the direct field to the Scala field mean
which essentially means make the scatter
the Scala field field scatter the direct
field the direct field scatter the uh
the scal of field by putting terms on
lran which couple them together for
example something like s dagger now I'm
writing something that won't work s
dagger Time
s it'll work but uh it's not Lenin
variant Sid dagger Time
s uh time
fi now this is not really quite
legitimate because it's not Lenin
variant if you want wanted to make it
Lenin variant I'm not going to explain
this tonight um we have to go back to
some of the dra Matrix Aly but you would
just put in a beta in here that would
make it Lenin variant right the beta is
just a matrix it doesn't change the
structure in the appreciable way it's
product of two size times a f and that
would give you an interesting field
Theory where F Fields scatter sigh and S
Fields scatter fi and the whole thing is
a big interacting mess when FS come on
size they scatter each
other yeah it's the same
beta it's the same beta right notice
sidei time M and
sidei same beta Time 5 so it's almost as
though M was being replaced by a scalar
field
here
uh this is the way oh if you you took
this
lran it would generate both the
equations of motion for SII and for
fi there would be a DA equation with an
extra term proportional to fi and a a uh
a scal of field equation with an extra
term that would have SAR s in it so this
is the pattern this is the way uh
Quantum field theories are
expressed they're codified by writing
down a grangian L grangian is a thing
which uh which in a very simple way
expresses all of the content all the
Dynamics all of the interactions between
these
fields all right those that's classical
field Theory classical wave packets
scattering other classical wave packets
what about Quantum field
Theory all right so I'm going to tell
you very briefly what
uh what this has to do with interaction
between particles we've already talked
at length about the scattering of
particles and how it is represented for
example by products of fields fields are
built up out of creation and
Annihilation operators okay so if you
take a
field for example and uh I don't know
let's take a simple example F
cubed what does that represent when you
think about it in terms of creation and
Annihilation
operators fi will contain both creation
operators let's call them A+ plus a
minuses this is very
schematic no detail it'll contain
various creation and Annihilation
operators and when it's cubed it will
contain all kinds of terms terms which
can absorb or annihilate three particles
that's the a uh the a minus Cube term
terms which can create three particles
terms which can eat two particles and
spit out a third and so forth so five
cubed has a meaning in terms of
particles coming in and particles going
out particle comes in two particles go
out at a point
x that's what F cubed of X represents
from a quantum mechanical point of view
okay I cubed of X represents one
particle coming in and splitting into
two at the point x but there are many
terms in adding up 5 cubed of X the
various terms correspond to possible
things which look like this
namely two particles coming in one
particle going out there's a possibility
of three particles going out just
produced at the uh at the origin three
particles coming in what else have I
missed
anything I think that's it one particle
goes to two two particles go to
one no particles go to three and three
particles uh disappear that's the kind
of thing which would be cified by 5
cubed of
X in
fact the lran
represents the some of the terms
represent interaction like this the
other terms the quadratic terms the the
the higher Powers here represent
interactions like this the quadratic
terms where are they 5^ 2 and here these
represent just the motion of a particle
and the motion of AN undisturbed
particle so let's see how that
works uh let's
take let's take uh a term
here's a terminal grangian derivative of
f with respect to
x² let me think of it the following way
the derivative of
fi is equal to F at one point minus fi
at a neighboring Point let's call it X
Prime that's what a derivative is Right
a derivative is basically a um uh a
difference of a field at two neighboring
points and again
schematically
so
squared that's what F derivative of f
with respect to X stands
for this
is put the one let's put the 1/2
here all right this is 12 5 of
x^2 plus 12
f of x Prime
squar but the important point is the
term which is uh f of x f of x
Prime these two terms are not very
interesting what do they do they absorb
a particle at a point and produce
another particle at exactly the same
point they might eat two particles at
the same point or they might uh take an
incoming particle at point x absorb it
and then just spit it back out at the
same point so they don't move the
particle around they just uh they're
sort of passive more or less passive
this term here absorbs a particle at X
Prime and REITs it at Point X or vice
versa in other words what it does is it
moves a particle from point x to X prime
it absorbs it if it finds it at X Prime
and and then REITs it at Point at point
x so what is it then it's a if this is
point x and this is point x prime it
just moves a particle from X to X
Prime that's the nature of these
quadratic terms in the lanan they move
particles from one point to another if
you wanted to imagine the motion of a
particle from one point to a distant
point you might simply multiply these
terms in lran together many
times uh so that the first time would
move the particle from X to X Prime next
time it would move it from X Prime to XP
Prime X Prime to XLE Prime and so forth
but stated simply the quadratic terms in
the lran Govern the motion of the
undisturbed particle that's what they do
uh they are connected with free motion
of the
particle on the other hand the nonlinear
terms the nonlinear terms mean the terms
which are cubic for example and you
could have higher terms they could be
quartic they take particles and bring
them together and scatter them or
annihilate them and create new
particles so that's what the lran does
as I said it codifies these interactions
these uh these processes
in a very very condensed
way
um question yeah when you're taking that
to you don't have to worry
about which thatti you don't have Tove
yeah we do certainly we do uh we could
call a difference between the distance
from X to X Prime let's just call it
distance L and we put an L Square
downstairs
so right you do have to put a a
numerical factor in there but the
numerical Factor doesn't change anything
it it doesn't change what these things
do number is just a number uh it still
has the effect of removing a particle at
X Prime and making it reappear at X
okay oh what does the mass term do uh
the mass term which is just m^2 5^
2 ALS Al is sort of like these terms
here it's also something which absorbs
and emits a particle at the same point
you can represent it let me represent it
by saying a particle comes in m^ s/ 2 a
particle comes
in and a particle goes out at the same
point x in comes in and goes
out so this Mass term m^2 x^2 it doesn't
move the particle around it just absorbs
it and REITs it okay absorbs it or just
just it counts particles really it just
tells you there's a particle there uh
but strictly speaking it absorbs a
particle and REITs it from the same
point right that's the uh that's the
nature of
the um Mass
term now we are of course drawing
diagrams and these diagrams are really
nothing but Fineman diagrams
we're not going to go into the depths of
findan diagramm ly it's not the it's not
important to where we're going to
go of course it is important to really
understanding uh particle physics but uh
let me just illustrate one more little
finding
diagram one more diagram describing uh a
particle process this is an important
one this is the basic process of quantum
electrodynamics quantum electrodynamics
describ is a is a description of
electrons and photons electrons and
photons electrons described by the
direct
field now first of all the direct field
for an electron is composed out of
creation uh let's see fi is itself
composed only out of annihilation
operators it's composed out of
annihilation operator so let's write it
as C I guess C minus
but in the expression for S there's a
sum over all the possible momentum and
all the possible momenta and properties
of the electron in particular there are
Annihilation operators for particles
with positive energy let's just write it
this way for and also Annihilation
operators for particles of negative
energy
remember the dra equation has Solutions
with both positive energy and negative
energy and there are Annihilation
operators in s for positive energy and
for negative energy s dagger has
creation operators C plus also for
positive
energy
and for negative
energy that's just what the direct
equation is that's what just the direct
field is creation operators and
Annihilation operators now we do a
little
switch this is the annihilation operator
for a particle for an electron of
negative energy it removes a part
removes an electron of negative
energy absolutely equivalent to removing
a particle of negative energy is putting
in is adding a particle
of adding an anti-particle of positive
energy the removal of a particle of
negative energy is the same as the
addition of an antiparticle of positive
energy that's this filling the daxi sort
of thing and so forth and so this
operator over here the annihilation
operator for particle of negative energy
can be
relabeled it can be relabeled as a
creation
operator for an anti-particle
of positive
energy let's indicate now that this is
for an
electron and this is for a
positron okay so the direct field
contains Annihilation operators for
electrons and creation operators for
positrons likewise Sid dagger contains
creation operators for
electrons and Annihilation operators for
positrons it's just a switch of
terminology a switch of
notation uh to represent the fact that a
positron is a hole in the negative
energy electron
C okay so now let's write down what the
basic interaction of quantum
electrodynamics is the basic interaction
of quantum electrodynamics
uh
involves s Daga
s and the photon field the photon field
is the electromagnetic field the vector
potential of the photon field if you
want to put things in correctly the
vector potential is a um is a vector so
it needs a vector
index and then we have to make a vector
out of side dagai we do that with the
direct
matrices and uh
the
well let's see let's let's write it
correctly it's Saga
s times the time component of the vector
potential a KN plus s Daga alpha s times
the space components of the
electromagnetic field what is this thing
I call a
the thing I call a is just the field
operator for
photons right it's just a field operator
for photons photons of course are
particles which have a directionality
their
polarization their polarization is a
little Vector so photons have in
addition to a position and a momentum or
a momentum they have a little
orientation they carry a little flag
with them which points in a certain
direction it's their
polarization and so in other words they
have a little bit of a vector character
to them and that's what this Vector is
it's just a polarization of the
photon right um what does this
do this absorbs an
electron let's see it absorbs an
electron it can emit a
positron let's see no I can emit an
electron let's see this one times this
one side diag Time s can absorb an
electron and then Reit the
electron and at the same
time emit a
photon yeah that's a term in the lran
that's a term in the lran is that a scal
yeah it is a scaler uh okay so let's uh
let's go back to the direct
equation you can make make scalars by
multiplying vectors together who asked
me yeah you make scalars for example by
multiplying vectors together right right
given two vectors B mu and a mu you can
make a scalar like
so yes you got yeah let's now let's now
right we have AMU but we don't have a
vector composed out of the size but we
do have a vector composed out of the
size so let me tell you what the vector
composed out of the size
is it's just s dag AI is the time
component of it and side Daga alpha
s is the uh is the space component of it
that's it all right so Saga s gets
multiplied by the time component and
side Daga alpha s gets multiplied by the
space
component you add them together okay
right so that makes a scale
that makes a scaler and uh can we go
back to that other board which one the
one you just covered up by ping this
down on here
yeah yeah okay thank you yeah now what
does a have in it a has creation and
Annihilation operators for photons so
what we have here is product of creation
and creation oper yeah let me think
creation operators for
electrons and Annihilation operators for
positrons that's here here's
Annihilation operators for electrons and
creation operators for positrons and he
is creation and Annihilation operators
for
photons so it describes a whole variety
of different kinds of processes let's
draw some of them a whole variety of of
different kinds of processes in which
electrons positrons and so forth are
created and
annihilated for
example it can take an incoming electron
let's put a little arrow on the electron
to show uh to show its direction of
motion it can scatter it and emit a
photon what is that that's an
Annihilation operated from an electron a
creation operator for the electron and a
creation operator for the photon that's
what this is right we can also have
electron comes
in electron goes
out photon is absorbed by the electron
so here's emission of a photon here's
absorption of a
photon okay what else can we have we can
have let's let's label this electron
electron electron electron but we can
also have electron coming
in and positron coming in
uh e minus electron is a negatively
charged particle we'll call it e
minus here we can have an electron
coming in and a positron coming in
that's usually drawn in this way an
electron coming in is drawn with an
arrow upward a positron coming in is
drawn with an arrow downward and then if
you draw it that way it looks as though
the electron just turns around but it's
not really that's not really what's
going on what's going on is electron is
coming in and a positron is coming in
and a photon going off that's another
thing that's contained in this uh
combination when you multiply side Diaga
time side *
a more what else
uh electron
positron being produced by a photon all
these various processes are contained in
this one single expression here s Daga s
time a
and they all have the same coefficient
in front of them same numerical
coefficient in front of them and so all
these processes the probability for them
the amplitude for them the quantum
mechanical amplitude for them are all
related to each other simply by the fact
that the coefficient in front of them is
the same numerical value whatever it
happens to be what does it happen to be
the numerical coefficient in front of us
I didn't write it down we should write
it down
well it's the no it's not the fine
structure constant it's close it's just
the electric charge of the
electron yeah okay what is the electric
charge of an electron the electric
charge of a particle is basically the
amplitude it's the square the square
root of the probability that an electron
when it scatters emits a
photon an electron at every point along
its trajectory can emit a photon the
probability per unit time time along the
trajectory for it to emit a photon is uh
the probability is the square of the
electric charge so electric charge is
the square root of the probability it's
the amplitude for the uh for the photon
to be
emitted third one you
just it's also the probability for that
it's the same H it's the same yeah
electric charge has to be some kind of
scaling factor is it scaling Factor
probability isn't have a
unit it's the probability per unit
uh
uh it's a dimensionless it's actually a
dimensionless
quantity it's a dimensionless
quantity um an example of a a an example
would be an electron bangs into a wall
and say stopped sto dead what's the
probability that it emits a
photon what's the probability that its
energy or its momentum its energy goes
off as an as a
photon
question yeah so a electron of a given
energy plows into a wall is STO
dead what's the probability that its
momentum continues in the form of a of a
photon
and uh that's the electric the that's
the square of the electric
charge so that's the meaning of the
electric charge in um in quantum
mechanics in classical field Theory it's
just a coefficient in front of the uh
the interacting s and a
[Music]
Fields does the electric charge have
units uh no
okay
uh yes look the units for electric
charge were defined by people who
um well how much current goes through a
wire this sort of thing that sort of
thing in microscopic quantum mechanics
we usually Define the electric charge in
a dimensionless way uh we don't measure
it in terms of kums we measure it just
in terms of the charge of an electron
and units of the charge of the
electron um so it's dimensionless but
really what it is it's the dimensionless
probability that a particle which
collides with a wall inits a
photon and um it really is
dimensionless the only Dimensions that
you really need in physics are mass
length and time in fact you don't need
any Dimensions you can work in uh
dimensionless units for everything plunk
units they're called plunk units are
dimensionless and in plunk units
everything is dimensionless including
the electric
charge is there some use in grouping H
is there some use in grouping things
that have charge involved or grouping
yeah what does that mean grouping well I
uh I mean it's sometimes you'll
write equations that have several terms
which you can then
go through the whole process and then
pull them out by equating leftand and
right hand side like terms on left hand
left hand and right hand side
so um it sort of has it I don't know I'm
just asking I can't think of anything
like
that question about the the timing of
the creation of anation is timing is
that simultaneous l or is there any kind
of delay that comes out of the equations
not no not for these basic fundamental
processes not the the proc okay the
these operators are all evaluated at the
same space-time
Point all at the same SpaceTime point
which means that the electron is
absorbed reemitted and the photon is
emitted from exactly the same point is
that what you're asking yeah yeah okay
I guess what I was saying is you have
different kinds of conserved quantities
and they individually have to be
conserved oh yes that's true yeah the
various conserved quantities here would
include charge for example that has to
be conserved um in fact the conservation
of
charge is nothing but the sort of
continuity of these arrows if we had a
process like this that would be what
would that be that would be an electron
coming in and a positron going going out
no good then then a a negative charge
would turn into a positive charge so if
we represent the flow of charge by this
Arrow here then an electron moving
vertically upward time is upward of
course an electron would be represented
by an arrow going up a positron would be
represented by an arrow going
down uh we do not allow arrows to come
come together the rule is always
throughgoing arrows arrows come in and
go
out come in and go out come in and go
out and that is tantamount to the
conservation of
charge right the conservation of charge
is also ensured by the
um by the fact that we have one sigh and
One S
dagger a s either creates an electron or
annihilates a
positron that means or did I say that
wrong AI annihilates an
electron aai annihilates an electron or
creates a positron in either case it
increases the charge by one unit when it
annihilates electron that increases the
charge by one unit when it creates a
positron it increases the charge by one
unit side dagger does the opposite so s
increases the charge by one unit side
dagg
decreases the charge by one unit and so
whatever this term here governs in the
way of processes it conserves electric
charge
yeah so so the term in the box is the
lran in the Box here on the
right in Q yeah well I haven't written
the whole thing there's also the
terms like
this which govern the photon and the
direct equation these are the
interaction terms that's inter yeah
those are the interaction terms right I
haven't bothered to write the uh the
quadratic terms so the I don't think
it's technically accurate but in my
education my undergraduate ucation
classical mechanics you always had the
feeling that the leing was something you
could figure out from understanding the
classical physics and there's a right
answer that you canuse and then a little
bit from what I think I'm hearing you
say and then what I've done in Reading
inside is that quantum mechanics line
isn't something you can produce it's
something you guess at you find out if
it's right by looking at the experiment
when did you have a deduced Grand un
classical mechanical system well
actually just looked in the back of my
palm from the exam
yeah but it was something that uh was
defined in my memory was it was a
difference between the kinetic energy
and potential yeah it is right
in fact here's kinetic energy of the
field here's potential energy of the
field this uh these spatial gradients
are kind of generalization of kinetic
energy kinetic energy means proportional
to square of time
derivatives potential energy means not
no
derivatives so that's exactly what it is
kinetic energy minus potential energy
and then is it exactly the same in B
yeah yeah right it's is the same in
quantum
mechanics is not a miracle no it's not a
miracle the quantum mechanical lran is
much more fundamental than the classical
mechan mechanical you start with a
quantum mechanical system described by
some L grangian and then in the limit of
large numbers of quanta you work out its
classical Behavior the uh remarkable
property here is that if the this kind
of lran here governs the quantum
mechanics that when you go to the large
number of Quant it will also govern the
classical wave equations that's not
obvious but uh it's true as far as how
physicists find out what Lans are what
the lran of systems
are well of course sometimes they guess
them on the basis of uh deeper
Theory and sometimes they get it right
and sometimes they don't get it right
but uh we know the lran of quantum
electrodynamics with extreme Precision
we know the lran of uh the standard
model of particle physics with extreme
Precision how do we know it we know it
from experiment we know it by colliding
particles together and working out just
what kinds of basic interactions it
takes to describe those uh those
interactions between particles so
there's a little bit of an art there but
when you do Collide particles together
and see what comes out you are looking
pretty directly at
these question find diagrams if you is
it always the case or not if you rotate
them they still be valid
yeah yeah rotate from here to
here mhm
yeah rotating means uh right yeah right
I think I left something
out I left out the possibility that
um an electron and a positron can come
together and a photon also be absorbed
at the same point so you can take any
one of these legs and push them up push
them down and it's still a valid uh
right quite remarkable I mean that uh
that one simple term can describe all
these different processes
any questions that one that you just did
that that sort of says that the proton
comes together with a positron and an
electron and results in nothing
right well of course
yeah several lectures back I showed you
how energy conservation
um uh is derivable by integrating such
processes over all time do you remember
that when we integrated the amplitude
for such a process over time we found
energy conservation when we integrated
it over space we found momentum
conservation this is the basic process
if we took that process and calculated
the amplitude for it and then integrated
it over all the places where the process
could
happen that integration would ensure
energy and momentum would be
conserved If energy and momentum is
conserved this kind of thing can't
really
happen it can't really happen because it
would violate the conservation of
energy okay so we have a little more
work to do after we've written down this
diagram expressed an amplitude for it we
have to integrate it over everywhere
with equal probability and that makes
sure the energy and momentum are
conserved
happen where out of nothing you get El
and yeah
[Music]
yeah I'm not quite sure what you're
saying are you saying that when we
integrate over time excluded processes
will automatically go away
yeah
Z question
over on the left side there things like
the partial of the field with respect to
time
and left side of what here yeah yeah and
then over on the right side the field is
expressed in creation Annihilation
operator
yes can you take the the partial respect
to time of the creation operator no you
don't take the okay good question
remember you don't take the derivative
of the creation
operator the
field looks like sums or integrals of
creation operators or Annihilation
operators with things like e to the I KX
e to Theus I Omega T right you're
differentiating these things not these
things these things don't depend on
position yeah they're like constants
they're like constants here's what
you're differentiating these objects
here that's why you pull down factors of
K and Omega by
differentiating
yeah let me give you another some other
examples of
interactions other kinds of processes
which exist in nature which can be
described by this kind of field
Theory uh protons neutrons and mesons
protons neutrons and mesons form a
system which is fairly similar to
Quantum electrodynamics so similar in in
spirit protons are firion neutrons are
fion they're described by exactly the
same kind of fields as uh as electrons
so let's give them names sa proton s
Neutron and then the other objects in
the theory are mesons P mesons are an
interesting collection of mesons what
are P
mesons they are we'll learn as we go on
that they're Quark anti- Quark pairs but
we're not interested in that now let's
uh let's just think of them as
particles um they're Scala particles
these are direct particles and pons are
Scala particles they come in three
varieties pi+ Pi minus and Pi
0 what is the plus minus and zero the
electric charge the electric charge of a
pi plus is plus one unit one unit in
units of electron uh electron um charges
this one is negatively charged and this
one is electrically neutral the proton
is positively charged the neutron is
neutral okay so let me give you examples
of some interactions which do occur in
nature there's side dagger proton
Let's uh s dagger
proton s Neutron let's see now uh s
Neutron uh absorbs a neutron and creates
a proton let's put what do we have to
put here a
Pon uh is it pi+ or Pi minus let's see
let's try pi
plus all right this absorbs a positively
charged
peson and oh I think I have it wrong Pi
minus it absorbs a negatively charged
Pon Pi
minus emits a
neutron
and absorbs a proton do I have that
right no I don't absorbs a
neutron and emits a pro and emits a
proton
and this does not look possible because
it looks like a negative charge went to
a positive charge so I think I want a
pi+ here okay this is one interaction
which occurs in nuclear physics this is
one interaction which occurs between
mesons and nucleons nucleons are protons
and neutrons and it's described like
this this of course is not a really
fundamental interaction the real thing
is
quirks okay and we're going to break
this down into processes in terms of
quirks but if we didn't know about
quarks and when we didn't know about
quarks we represented protons and
neutrons in terms of fundamental Fields
pons in terms of fundamental fields and
we would write down things like this
what else can be there uh side diag
Neutron s proton and Pi minus this
absorbs let's see this
absorbs a pi minus and a
proton and gives off a neutron
[Music]
and Saga proton s proton Pi 0 and also
sidea Neutron s Neutron and
pi0 all right what do these things
describe they describe proton goes to
Neutron plus a
pi+ but of course the same vertex here
describes many
processes it uh the same one describes
proton anti
Neutron anti- Neutron anti- Neutron I'll
represent just by a bar emitting a
pi+ a whole variety you can push the
legs up and down when a leg is Switched
you have to replace it by an anti
particle so if you take an outgoing
Neutron and take that outgoing Neutron
switch it around his proton coming in it
becomes an anti- Neutron coming in the
outgoing Neutron when switched around
upside down becomes an incoming anti-
Neutron so here's an incoming proton
incoming anti- Neutron they annihilate
each other and create a positively
charged
peson so you can work out what all the
different interactions that take place
between protons pons and
neutrons and basically all of them can
happen as long as they conserve
charge as long as they conserve charge
they all happen they're all part of
nuclear physics all possibilities and
they're codified in a small number of
terms side dagger proton side Neutron pi
plus and so forth so that's another
example of where this uh where this sort
of
Technology was important in the early
days before we knew about
quirks um the fact that the proton and
neutron are made up out of
quirks well the size of the a quark
Quark distribution is sort of like a
atom like electrons going around an atom
and so forth but it's much much smaller
it's much much smaller the proton and
because it's smaller it means at some
level you can think of it as a point
particle in other words for all
measurements interactions and so forth
which don't break it up which don't
break up the
proton uh you can think of the proton as
pretty much a point particle in that
approximation you pretend protons and
neutrons are described by fundamental
fields of course what would happen if
you hit the proton and neutron too hard
is it'll break up uh it'll sort of break
up into
quirks if it breaks up into quarks then
you the you won't get you won't get away
with the description in which the proton
and neutron are described by simple
Fields you'll have to remember that it's
made of
quarks all right um what happens when
El come together is the same type of
expression you use for the when proton
and electron come together
yeah okay
um yeah yeah there's of course another
vertex in uh involving protons and the
other vertex involving protons also
involves the photon here I just told you
about protons neutrons and
pons but because protons are charged
there's another vertex which
is proton
Photon
proton you can't have proton goes to
Neutron in a photon that doesn't
conserve
charge so proton goes to proton and a
photon is another allowed process and
also electron goes to electron and
photon is an allowed process so a
possible process that can take place
when a uh when a proton encounters an
electron
is the
proton can emit the
photon and the electron absorb the
photon we haven't talked about building
up more complicated processes yet we're
going to talk about building up more
complicated processes but you can see
the the pattern you can build processes
out of these Elementary units the
elementary units are these vertices and
you build up
uh two different SpaceTime points how
would you write the L for that no that's
not this this process is not described
it's the
point units that you start with that are
described by the uh lanan okay this
corresponds to the product of the lran
at two different points okay
so the lran is some basic unit of
interaction which tells you that a
proton is absorbed and emitted at a
point and the
photon right that's the interaction term
that's side Daga proton s proton and and
a then there's the quadratic terms which
move the photon
along remember they were the things
which move the photon along from point
to point they can act many many times
moving the photon from one place to
another and then the photon can be
absorbed over
here yeah we're not uh we're clearly not
deriving all of this in any sense from
first principles I'm just telling you
that these basic Elementary processes
out of which you build everything are
codified in the in L grangian and L
grangian always describes things which
take place at a point or perhaps a pair
of neighboring
points two kinds of terms in lran and
here here here they are this one here
describes a thing at a point something
comes in and something goes out from the
same point the other terms in lran
involve derivatives and they correspond
to things at very close by neighboring
points motion of a particle from one
point to
another uh no action at a distance in uh
in Quantum field Theory at
worst there or not at worst it's a good
thing but you can move a particle from
one point to a very very infinitesimally
close point or you can have processes
taking place at a specific individual
point right there are no things in lran
which take a particle from one point and
put it at another Point those processes
are built
up uh built up out of more Elementary
processes in this case something taking
place at this point something taking
place at this point and then a large
number of little processes moving the
electron uh proton from one point to the
next the The only has terms at one of
those at one point then one point or a
pair of neighboring points if it has
derivatives so that describes that
proton proton electron exchange yeah
just has terms for proton
[Music]
electron there's no term in Lan which
describes this whole
process this process is described by a
large number of basic units large number
of basic units is a process taking place
at this point that's side dager proton s
proton an emission of a
photon and then basic Elementary process
which move the particle from one point
to a neighboring point to a neighboring
point and then the absorption of proton
over
here but all of these are in the lran
that you write for this each individual
each individual processes in the lran
but you have to compound them together
to make up the general
process by compound you mean multiply
yes yes lanan can act any number of
times at different uh remember the lran
itself is made out of fields fields are
made out of creation and Annihilation
operators and the lrin can
occur at each point of space next point
of space next point in space and so
forth and build up whole processes so
the L grangian is not something which is
a final answer it describes the basic
units and elements that uh that compound
themselves together by product exactly
as you said per form uh yeah so the Le
also has time terms in it so time
derivative terms time terms and so if
you try and extend that to process are
taking place over certain
distances where you know under
conditions where time is affected by
relativity or something like that can't
you have problem can't you have what
can't you have problems or are we just
not
in in the case of Relativity
yeah what do you I'm not sure what
you're asking um you if you were running
your if you were doing your um
compounding of
BR in very close to the Horizon of black
hole
that still describe the process
[Music]
well you you really want to talk about
black holes
no is not well describ by Quantum F
Theory how far can you how far can this
INF test
distances well you have to think about
limit so when I said and time distance
and time I guess we're all having
trouble trying to think what what are
Fields how
think uh the fields are symbols
which uh operators they're operators
which make processes happen all right
they're processes the basic processes or
basic Elementary processes they absorb a
particle or they emit a particle that's
all they do they absorb it take it in at
one point they they take it in at one
point or spit it out from the same point
multiplying Fields together can bring in
one particle and spit out another
one um h let's put it this way a single
field by
itself can absorb a particle or spit out
a particle the product of two Fields can
absorb a particle and spit out a
particle you understand the difference
between or and
N uh in one case either the field or
single power of the field absorbs a
particle or it emits a
particle two powers of the field absorb
and emit a partic
and properly describ describes that
mechanism for every point it's just a
code it's just a code right it's just a
code for uh for the elementary processes
which you have to compare together well
it does have time derivatives as well as
yeah space derivatives it
does okay so you thinking terms of
SpaceTime you think in terms of
SpaceTime x and t and you think of the
trajectory of a
particle as being built
up uh motion of a particle as being
built up at many Little Steps now of
course we have to take limits we take
limits by um by
replacing derivatives differences by
derivatives and so forth but let's think
about uh little differences rather than
derivatives we break up the trajectory
into a lot of little pieces and then a
particle is absorbed at this point
reemitted at this point so it's jumped
from one point to SpaceTime to another
point of SpaceTime and it's absorbed at
this point again and reemitted and
reemitted at this point in the process
it hops from point to point to point to
point
now um in the limit that we subdivide
this trajectory into an infinitely small
series of steps here the number of
processes goes to
Infinity all right so there are limits
involved but the simplest way to think
about it is to subdivide everything into
little pieces and think of basic
Elementary units of motion from one
point to a neighboring point it's an
effective way to think about it in fact
Quantum field Theory really always does
have to be uh defined by dividing up
space time into lots of little cells
that's the way you really Define it you
break it up into lots of little
cells having broken it up into a lot of
little cells
yeah I don't want to interrup no go
ahead I was just going to bring it back
to the original question so when you put
all this
together out when you put um so you can
overlay these fields on top of each
other to describe processes that now you
can for any given point in time and
space what will happen at any given time
and point in space and you can make it
as complex as you want yeah um the
question that I originally asked was if
now you combine them to describe a a
multi-step process as people were asking
about earlier yes as soon as that
multi-step process has like motion of
the particle that you were
describing where the quadratic term
allows for product theion but I mean
motion simply means Annihilation at one
point Creation in a
[Applause]
neighbor well I wasn't just you were
talking about the quadratic term mean
product moving as they move apart if
like really high energies can there be
are there problems with like things like
time dilation or stuff like that takes
place ining you have to take account of
true when there's more and more distance
between that
all of that is rather automatic if you
uh if the lran is a scaler everything
will be lorensen variant and all of that
kind of thing about time dilation and so
forth will be
automatic you won't have to worry about
it but I'm not sure exactly what
question you're asking so I can't answer
it
[Applause]
um what is the connection
between these operators
between the creation Annihilation
operators in the field and the classical
mechanic operators of position momentum
and the indeterminist
Heisenberg
uncertainty
um the connection between creation and
Annihilation and Heisenberg uncertainty
all right heisen ber uncertainty is
another way of saying you either
describe things in terms of position or
momentum not both right all
right the in terms of creation and
Annihilation operators the creation
operators and Annihilation operators are
either functions of position or
functions of
momentum and um the field operator s of
X is the creation operator for particle
at point x it is made
up out of field operators let's say
a which are functions of momentum times
e to the I blah blah blah blah
blah so creation operators are either
creation operators for a particle of
momentum P or creation operators for a
particle of M of position X but they are
not creation operators for particles of
position X and momentum
P we never have operators which create
particles of momentum P at position X
either their functions of X or their
functions of p and the relationship
between the functions of X and the
functions of p is simply Foria
transform Foria transform is the essence
of the uncertainty
principle and what it says uh is that
the is that build a function which is
localized in position you have to use a
lot of momenta to build a function which
is localized in momenta you well it's
it's going to be spread over X but this
is just exactly the same thing as it is
in Ordinary Elementary quantum
mechanics uh you either have something
which is a function of X or a function
of p and nothing which is a function of
X and P that's
all uh you were describing how you
subdivided the XT space inste of
could you complete that or yeah could
you just finish that
explanation yeah I mean it's okay at
some level it's no different than what
you do in In classical physics in
classical physics how do you define
derivative you define derivative by
dividing up space into little cells and
then Define differences that's what a
derivative is now in classical physics
you can really just take the limit
rather smoothly and forget the fact that
it uh that it originated from a very
discrete picture in Quantum field Theory
it's more problematic you really do have
to define the theory from the beginning
by dividing up space into little
cells and having divided into little
cells in each
cell the field operator is now not a
function of continuous position it's now
a function of which one of these cells
you're
in derivative become
differences and the quadratic terms in
the hamiltonian take a particle from one
cell remove it and put it into the other
cell okay so that's how you move that's
why you said the derivatives with
respect to moving from place to place
yeah okay yeah
right right so Define the theory by
first dividing up
space placing your field operators one
or however many in each cell and then
the basic quadratic interactions will
absorb a particle from one cell and put
it into the neighboring
cell
right then in the end you take a limit
where you take the cells to be
infinitely
small okay so in terms of a discrete
picture a process might absorb an
electron over here the electron which
happened to have come from a neighboring
cell and so forth the electron came from
a neighboring cell absorb it over here
emit it over
here and emit a
photon then the photon will hop from
cell to cell to cell by the quadratic
terms also the electrons will hop from
cell to cell the uh the electron the
photon will hop from cell to cell to
cell where it might meet an electron at
the so there's just basically two kinds
of things hopping from one point to
another and interactions which absorb
some particles and emit them from the
same point and and and the mass term
here this m² 5^ 2 it can be thought of
as a kind of interaction where a
particle comes into a cell and is
emitted from the same cell with a
coefficient M squ an
amp it's like there a relation between
the size of the cell in F cost no no no
in the end you want to shrink that size
of the cell tell to zero to very
precisely Define the
theory right Quantum field theory is
kind of the
limit of a
discrete theory in which motion is
replaced by hopping and in which space
is
the so the the function of of taking a
product of the
lran is is basically it's a
probabilistic type of a thing contingent
probability that in order for this
process to go through you have to have
something going from here to there to
there yeah as opposed to it's not a time
thing CU it's over space time it's over
space
time that's put in the cells
right you put your joint probability NE
in each cell
right yes each cell each cell that's
right and then
the process is what goes up the
KE well the process is best thought of
is a thing that happens in space
time yeah I mean you can
yeah
[Music]
progresses is it interesting to think
about what the initial state of such a
system might be or is it it's sure it's
very interesting but uh
but that's that's determined what by
what the experiment decides to prare in
a
laboratory you think just just for
Illustrated purposes what those might
some some simple initial condition is
sure electron comes out of a hot
filament and how would that how would
you represent that in this this formula
at the position of the filament the
field operator operates which creates an
electron at the filament
right so the initial and final
conditions the absorpt the initial the
initial conditions are simply the start
of the the start of the particles coming
in and that happens at whatever the
source of the particles are the
sources the uh the final conditions are
just described by where the detectors
are okay so uh and in each case creation
operators or field operators located at
the points of the filaments which create
the hot electrons describe the emission
of the electrons from those points and
the absorption of the electrons that the
detectors are also described by field
operators at the positions of the
[Music]
detectors it's not good Cricket though
to do field Theory like it's not okay to
if you were to develop your model of
SpaceTime to just put the
lran for the EM for the emitters
where the emitters are right you need to
put it across your whole that's right
that's right you describe that's right
you start you
start the easy way to think about it is
to start with the vacuum now the initial
state is not the vacuum the initial
state is some particles present produced
by the uh by the um filaments or
whatever the sources of the particles
are so those you represent by a bunch of
creation operators or field operators at
the position of the uh of the sources si
si s that's the initial State the final
States also a vacuum and then
Annihilation
operators I don't know side dagger side
dagger side dagger I guess uh like that
and then stuff takes place in between
these are just the initial and final
States but what goes on in between is
determined by this lunian what goes on
in between is determined by the lran so
you might put in many factors of the
lran
here right each factor of the lran might
absorb a particle and emit a particle at
a neighboring
point with enough powers of lran here
you can take all of the particles and
move them simultaneously from one point
to
another
right so the absor the EM the the
starting point would be some particles
which were produced over
here that would be
this the final things were the final
States might be particles absorbed over
here come in and what happens in
between is governed by the Dynamics
which is just this L grangian repeatedly
acting and taking particles from one
point to another creating annihilating
particles and then at the end uh the
detector
them in principle an infinite number of
infinite
number so are you are you in some sense
integrating over those L integrating
over the positions of them
yeah
you is that what you me integrating over
the
positions not sure I'm not trying to
give you the finding rules I'm not
trying to explain exactly how you use
these things the main point for us the
main point for us is that the
interactions the basic
interactions are coded in simple
Expressions involving field operators
the reason we're going there is because
that makes it very easy to think about
symmetries for
example this term in the lonian has a
symmetry
what is that symmetry we've talked about
it before the Symmetry is the symmetry
of multiplying
s by e to the I time Theta where Theta
can be anything Sid dagger at the same
time gets multiplied by E to Theus I
Theta and S * s dagger will be
unaffected by this change of the defin
by this change in side Sor I'm sorry
yeah so here's a symmetry a symmetry of
this lran is multiplying Side by a phase
multiplying side Dagger by the complex
conjugate phase and doing nothing to a
that will not change the sran that
becomes a symmetry what is that symmetry
associated with well it's just
associated with the statement that you
have equal number of size and side
daggers if you had different numbers of
size and side daggers this would not be
invariant
all right what is the Symmetry that uh
that has to do with equal number of
sides and side daggers charge
conservation so the point is the the um
the basic utility of this for us will be
to write down Expressions where we can
read off the symmetries and from the
symmetries read off the conservation
laws that's really what this is all
about the symmetries the conservation
laws and the very very basic uh
primitive processes which take place at
each point of SpaceTime that's what the
lanine contains in it what do you do
with it well you multiply it together
many many times which is just the same
as saying you repeat basic processes in
any order that's allowed anything that
can happen that's allowed to happen by
conservation laws and all of that is
described by taking this L grangian and
just hitting and hitting and hitting and
hitting so that you take the initial
state and eventually evolve it into the
final
State what is the output of this the
output of this is an amplitude but that
amplitude is governed by fineman's rules
which we're not going to take up now in
any case uh we probably will at some
point but for tonight all I really
wanted to do was to show in
um
uh to show you how basic processes are
coded by a lran
and
um and we will use that to see how
symmetries and conservation laws are
connected with each other not
theight yeah uh do
the with these operators play any
Ro
sure sure I mean let's take the case of
the electromagnetic field the igen
values of the electric electric field
or uh field operators in general are the
possible measurable values of the field
if you measured
it uh you do measure electromagnetic
fields
there when you measure how do you
measure an electric field you measure an
electric field by putting a Charged
particle into it and seeing how it
accelerates you can get different values
those values are the igen values of the
electric field
[Music]
it's kind of interesting the Electric
magnetic field field operators in
general are built up out of creation and
Annihilation operators creation and
Annihilation operators don't commute
with each
other that means in general that the
field operators don't commute with each
other what what uh what's the not to
commute the FI has to commute with f
because it's the same thing
right what's the commutator between a
thing and
itself zero always all right so the
commutator of five with itself is always
zero but not so because you can take the
commutator of fi at one point with Fi at
another point a neighboring or some
other point could be at a different
point it could be a neighboring
Point each one of those FES is made out
of creation and annihilation operators
they're not the same operators because
they're evaluated at different positions
of space or time and in general they
will not commute what is the meaning of
this the meaning of this is that in
general you cannot simultaneously
measure the field operator with two
different positions there are
uncertainty relations in measuring
fields or time derivatives of fields at
two different positions of
SpaceTime so uh you asked me about I
think you asked about that did you ask
me about that yeah you asked me about
the field operator as a thing which uh
which can be measured well yes the field
operators can be measured there igen
vectors and igen values play the usual
role as in quantum mechanics and the
commutation relations tell you
limitations on being able to measure two
things simultaneously so all the
standard rules of quantum mechanics
appli to this system
[Music]
um electrodynamics we learned
that the electromagnetic field is
measured in volts the electromagnetic
field is measured in volts in volts okay
Vols per volt
per yeah electric field is measured in
volts per meter is the photon fi in Vols
also field is measured in the same thing
yeah but it's a it's a poor way to think
about it I mean you don't want to think
about volts and meters when you're
thinking about the if you're better off
measuring it in terms of number of
photons and uh
uh it's not profitable to think of the
electromagnetic field when you're
thinking about microscopic physics and B
and volts and the
meters I you could if you want
probably also not proper to think about
the quantum field Theory when you're
trying to wire your house
[Music]
yeah just um just to like summarize
today could you say that uh the idea
behind what you're saying is that the
way to study all these things is
basically by taking the Brans and
building block and you put them together
in different ways and that's yeah that
the general idea
y processes can happen over processes
can repeat one to the next to the next
in other words you can have a process
followed by a process followed by a
process followed by a process the um
basic all processes are built up out of
basic elements and the basic elements
have one important feature that they are
associated with points of space or
neighboring points of space neighboring
points of space are pretty close
together so that's another way of saying
that they're local that nothing there's
no action at a
distance that uh that the basic
indivisible processes are local and
non-local processes such as a photon
going from one place to another are
built up out of these local processes
yeah when you have a creation of a
photon right and then it moves across B
and you got these lrin that you think
about is there some simplification by
compacting many of them can you come up
with like a transformation that kind of
represents all of them right so that you
can get from so basically you can break
it down to three processes the
generation the movement and the
ter the creation the destruction roughly
speaking roughly speaking you simply
take this is not exact but it's it's
roughly speaking you take one plus let's
call it the uh the interaction lran L
interaction at point
x and now you multiply them together at
all points of space
X1 X2 X3 and X4 and so forth what do you
get then well first of all you just get
one that's not interesting that doesn't
do anything and then you
get all the all the possible terms in
which every Factor here is one except
one except one factor that will give you
the sum of the lran over all
space okay let me show you what I
mean you take
one plus the lran at point
x do the same thing at point x Prime 1
plus Lan at point x
Prime 1 plus the Lan at point x double
Prime and you do this for every point in
space now every point in space means
every point on this grid let's take just
two terms let's just take two factors
what does it give you it gives you 1
plus L at Point X Plus L at point x
prime plus L at at point x * L at point
x Prime right all right what does this
represent this represents nothing
happening this represents a basic for
example a basic interaction at point
x this represents the same basic
interaction taking place at point x
Prime so this could be nothing this
could be particles absorbed and emitted
at point x this could be particles
absorbed and emitted at point x Prime
and what about this
one right so right this could be
something else happening over here and
this one would
represent particle absorbed at point
x something
emitted and
then right given that first one has
happened then the second one happened
well the first term here just represents
one process and only one process Tak the
last terms says that something is
contingent on something else have having
happened well it just means both things
happen one after the other yeah okay so
represents two particles being absorbed
particle and then two particles being
you know you you see what it means and
um eventually by the time you multiply
all of these terms together you get an
infinite number of terms in which a
basic unit can happen at every point of
space once and then an infinite number
of terms where two points of space are
involved and then an infinite number of
terms where three points of space are
involved let's draw one where three
points of space are
involved two particles come in a
particle goes out another particle goes
out another particle that's only two
points of space space time and then
another vertex over here so that's two
particles in three particles
out I think what he was saying is that
if you have motion terms oh they're also
in here I'm just saying since you since
you have motion terms one motion term of
a movement from of a photon for a finite
distance takes an infinite number of
applications of the lran well that's
true but uh we uh begin so I'm I'm was
saying that well you kind of have
equations of motion for that part of the
lran and you can just Trace out the
motion or
something motion of a particle from here
and here to here will involve a bunch of
terms right this term will appear this
term will appear in this big product
somewhere in this big product there will
be a
term uh which involves L at point one
point L at the neighboring Point L at
the neighboring point that at the
neighboring point and which will
transport the particle from here to here
okay right so somewhere is in this big
product you'll
find exactly the right thing to uh to
take you from here to
here actually by many roots there will
be many okay first of all there will be
many many such terms which can take the
particle from here to here depending on
the orbit
uh the actual amplitude to go from here
to here is the sum of them all the
possible ways you can get from here to
Here by multiplying out this long string
of uh factors will give you a possible
Pro a possible process whereby the
particle can go from this point to this
point the uh the total amplitude the
thing that you square to get the
probability will be the sum of all ways
go that be consistent with the doubleit
the fraction yeah exactly right so when
you multiply out this big string of
terms here you will
find
uh terms corresponding to all possible
roots from here to
here the amplitude will be the sum of
all those ways of getting from here to
here and when you square it it there
will be interference terms in particular
if there are double
[Music]
SS the one come
from I just know say um where did it
come
from it's a trick to get all the
combinations yeah that's right it's a
trick to it's a trick to get all the
combinations it really comes from
finding path integral methods but you
can just think of it as a trick to write
down all the combinations uh
uh and that's that's what really this is
all about just all possible
combinations
of uh ways of going from one place to
another are described by this product
here I'm cheating a little bit when I
write this down this really a more
technical expression but this is close
to the right thing so I mean this is
we've done here is like we
from principle least action or
stationary action
right well okay in in quantum mechanics
it's not the principle yeah the
principle of stationary action good yeah
that's right uh the principle of no it's
not the principle of stationary action
it's in classical mechanics the
principle of stationary action picks out
a particular trajectory it picks out the
trajectory of let's say minimum action
this is the princip Le of summing over
trajectories where uh where the
amplitude for summing over the
trajectories is determined by the
action including going to Paris on the
way yes including going on Paris from
the way from uh uh my office to my house
so and you just said it's an art form
figure out how to express that no no no
it's an art form the figure out what
what the lran is once you know the L
grangian the rules are very
definite so sure has its art to it does
it does it does but uh only like any
other mathematics uh has its art you
have to be clever the the
um what what do we call it when you
don't know what you're doing and you're
groping and you're guessing and uh and
you art art yeah
um the the art form is in finding tricks
to to figure out what the lran is from
experimental data once you know it then
you use it in a very very precise uh
formalism to calculate
probabilities teacher
says research is what I I call what I
don't know what I'm doing
yeah but uh you know if somebody tells
you here is the
lran here is the process I'm interested
in two particles in four particles out
two particles come in from here four
particles go out over here calculate for
me uh the probability for that process
to happen then uh Quantum field theory
is an extremely precise tool there's no
ambiguities in how you use it uh it the
ambiguities or not the ambiguities but
the art form is in figuring out what
that lran is from experiment Al
data and
uh
yeah so the
[Music]
forms yeah big the the big book of
lrin
okay I think what you're asking me is
how complicated the lran of the world
is
um you know there's one at least in
physicist's Minds there is one lran that
governs everything now that may not
really be true but let's suppose that it
is and it contains a large number of
fields it contains all of the fields
describing all of the particles and all
of the interactions and it may have the
sum of many many terms like this
describing lots and lots of different
interactions but it's one
lran uh may be composed out of sums of
pieces which individually look like uh
recognizable uh
pieces but the whole thing is a one big
lran that governs all of nature now this
may be really false but that's the idea
that there's one big
lran with many terms in it that just
governs
everything one you got there one term
well yeah maybe a little better than one
term at a time but roughly speaking yes
um every time we discover a new particle
we discover a new field that has to go
into that lran every time we discover a
new process that's a new interaction in
lanan um so you might say well this
whole thing is a big giant mess and
indeed it is uh there are probably uh at
least a 100 different Elementary
particles things that we coal Elementary
particles uh 500 different terms in lran
in fact it's so bad that the kinds of
lonians that people write down to
describe the standard if if you wanted
to write down all the physics which is
known which means Quantum
electrodynamics uh the strong
interaction strong nuclear force Quantum
chromodynamics the weak
interactions uh gravity and everything
else you gr would fill not a book I
don't think but it would fill a couple
of uh couple of closely spaced page
pages are these fields what determine
the shape of the clavo manifold well let
look that the day you're going into uh
you're going Beyond basic Quantum field
Theory there you're talking now about um
those things which are outside the
framework of uh standard Quantum field
Theory right so all into one yeah and
then there's coupling constants the
coupling constants are the coefficients
in the
lran yeah so for example here's a
coupling constant the mass the mass
squared is also a kind of coupling
constant uh it's also a coefficient in
lran in various coefficients you could
have five to the 4th five to the 6 five
to the 500 each one would be a coupling
constant so
um it's a mess it's a big mess but once
you know the
lran you know a lot you deduce a lot of
different kinds of processes out of it
now do you have to know the whole thing
in order for example to study Quantum
electrodynamics well if you wanted it
with infinite Precision you would have
to know how the electron interacts with
all the particles all the different
kinds of particles through all of the
possible interaction
but in fact um qu quarks are not very
important to the way electrons behave
quarks are pretty much isolated from
electrons they don't uh they don't uh
mix too much with them and so you can
pretty much ignore quarks if you're only
interested in electrons and photons at
Atomic
energies you just don't have enough
energy uh to sense the tiny tiny uh
Quark structure and so practical
purposes you can often break off a piece
of this lran and say all the other
things in it are not terribly important
to what you're calculating break off
small pieces of lran and calculate with
it but in principle uh if you wanted
infinitely precise uh things about
photons and electrons you would just
need the whole thing this is not a
pretty picture I mean this is this is
really not a pretty picture the uh it
very much makes you feel that Quantum
field theory is some effective
description coming
from um like hydrodynamics or any other
effective description which
is coming from some more fundamental
physics and uh just what's the right
term
um uh effectively describing things at
some coar grained level that Quantum
Quantum field theory is probably just a
coar grained description of something
more
fundamental and uh as long as that's the
case it can be very very
complicated although
precise I think the word want is
phenomenological yeah yeah I think
that's the right word
right stand gravity also just like
you what what's officially called the
standard model leaves our gravity
um and then
I was going to ask you but you can you
know you can add gravity into the
standard model and talk about standard
model with
gravity if the higs I was going to ask
one mention going to see Rel stuff we
don't need that
General when you say relativistic that
means
what oh these LR are
relativistic right great
so if we were to look at thean in the
standard model we wouldn't see anything
Tak into
account relity general relativity this
does not take into account general
relativity special relativity it does
yeah this is spe this is the combination
of quantum mechanics and special
relativity if if all the particles are
massless except for the terms involving
the higs
basically you have what just terms which
are higs interactions that uh that have
like Mass terms for the other particles
yeah
um okay so I'll give
you I think we talked about this before
but I'll tell you again right so we see
that what the mass term is is it's the
coefficient of y^
s right
um supposing we had another field that
I'll call H all right and supposing in
the lren I had here let's write to write
down some terms H f^
squar now that's not quadratic that's
cubic so what does it describe it
describes a f in a f out and an H being
emitted
okay
um that's what this term does in L now
imagine there's more terms something
like V of
H now V is potential energy V is
potential energy it's the potential
energy of the field h supposing v of H
happens to be a function which looks oh
let's say something like this
here's H and V of H is such that the
minimum of the potential is not at H
equals z the minimum of the potential
energy defines the stable equilibrium
point
right the vacuum is a stable equilibrium
point so and for this particular
potential there might be two Minima and
the real vacuum would be
chosen to be one of these two
Minima this Minima has a nonzero value
of H so this vertex then
becomes just a this this vacuum value of
H here just becomes a number in the
vacuum and translates into the uh into
the um
yeah
um yeah last question does the standard
model capture the whole concept of
particle creation Annihilation oh
absolutely yeah oh
absolutely yeah
definitely for more please visit us at
stanford.edu